Guide to the Nelson and Beverly Nagai Collection of Asian-American History and Culture M1928
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Nelson and Beverly Nagai Collection of Asian-American History and Culture
circa 1968-1980
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Nagai, Nelson
Nagai, Beverly
M1928
7.5 Linear Feet: 10 boxes, 2 oversize folders
Publications & ephemera of late-20th century radical political activism centered in the Bay Area, with an emphasis on Asian-American activism. Includes correspondence, newspapers, pamphlets, periodicals, posters, printed ephemera, t-shirts, buttons, and videocassettes.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of publications & ephemera of late-20th century radical political activism, with an emphasis on Asian American protest movements. The collection includes the following material: Radical Asian community newspapers, most from the 1970s and 1980s; various pamphlets related to Communism, the African-American, Chicano and Puerto Rican communities, and American workers’ and radical Leftist movements; t-shirts with safety-pin buttons from the 1970s; large photographs of the sites of Japanese internment camps in California; and movie posters of films about Asians and Asian-Americans.
Biographical / Historical
Nelson Nagai was the chairperson of the constitution committee of Stockton’s Yellow Seed, a community service organization. While at Stanford University, Nagai also served as the chairperson of the Asian American Student Association. During the International Hotel struggle, Nagai served as the auditor of the International Hotel Tenants Association.
The original Kearny Street Workshop (KSW) storefront in San Francisco Chinatown, 1971, located on the ground floor of the International Hotel. At the time, the images produced by KSW's silkscreen and graphics artists were among the first to portray strong and bold images of Asian Americans. The group's work was a hallmark of the Asian American movement on the West Coast but it was also a place "where they felt they belonged," which is how Nelson Nagai described the Yellow Seed, a Stockton organization (see text below).
From an excerpt of "I Come From a Yellow Seed" by Nelson Nagai:
"[In 1969] it was decided that the Asian community needed a drop-in center for youth -- some place where they felt they belonged and an alternative to the pool hall [which had been boycotted because the white owner told Asians to leave the establishment]. So the Yellow Seed Center was born.
Quickly an organization was started around the center. [In 1971] the Yellow Seed received funding for a recreation center to serve the children of Asian cannery workers from the federal government. Our idea was to provide activities for Asian children so that they would not have to run the streets like we did."
From Snapshots of Asian America (KQED)
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audiovisual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nelson Nagai, 2012. Accession 2012-249.
Related Materials
Some items were catalogued individually and can be found on Searchworks at this link: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/catalog?q=%22The+Nelson+and+Beverly+Nagai+collection+of+Asian-American+history+and+culture.%22&search_field=subject_terms
University of the Pacific holds the Nelson Nagai And Grace Sumida Collection (MSS 329), whjich contains material collected by Nelson and his mother Grace.
Radicalism.; Asian-Americans -- History; Printed ephemera; Nagai, Nelson; Nagai, Beverly
- The Struggle Against Revisionism and Opportunism (Black Workers' Congress) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Party Building in the Heat of the Class Struggle" (Puerto Rican Revolutionary Workers) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Yellow Seed (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Nihonmachi Little Friends (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bay Area Asian Coalition Against the War (Box 1, Folder 5)
- International Hotel (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Stanford Asian-American Students' Association (Box 1, Folder 7)
- CANE (Committee Against Nihonmachi Eviction) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Asian Community Center (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Asian American Student Alliance (Stanford) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Left in Form, Right in Essence (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Unidentified Braille (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Unidentified Transparencies (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Lahing Pilipino (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Roadblocks to Community Building (Stockton Filipino Community Center) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- The Chicanos (NACLA) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- How Capitalism has been Restored in the Soviet Union (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The Energy Crisis and You (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Ideology of the Young Lords Party (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Communist Revolution: The Road to the Future, The Goal We Will Win (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Critique of the Black Nation Thesis (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Education to Govern (Box 2, Folder 7)
- A New Outlook on You on Me on Health (Box 2, Folder 8)
- From Trotskyism to Social-Imperialism (Box 2, Folder 9)
- The Anti-Marxist-Leninist Line of Progressive Labor (Box 2, Folder 10)
- A Polemic Against The Guardian's Revisionism (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Proletarian Internationalism or Revisionism (Box 2, Folder 12)
- The "New Economic Policy" (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Affirmative Action Discrimination (conference) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Defeat the "National Question" (New Voice) (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Beyond Welfare (Committee for Political Development) (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Wage Controls and How to Fight 'Em (United Front Press) (Box 2, Folder 17)
- The United Front Against War and Fascism (Gamma Publishing) (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Unite the Many, Defeat the Few (Guardian pamphlet) (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Workers' Viewpoint Journal (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Revolutionary Union (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Against Dogmatism on the National Question (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Campesinos Organizan su Union - ¡SI SE PUEDE! (Box 3, Folder 2)
- The Heritage of Sen Katayama (Box 3, Folder 3)
- For Working Class Unity and Black Liberation (Box 3, Folder 4)
- A Comment On The Statement Of The Communist Party (USA) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Delay Evictions (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Chinese-American Workers: Past & Present (Box 3, Folder 7)
- August 29th Movement (ATM) (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Statements of the Founding (League of Revolutionary Struggle) (Box 3, Folder 9)
- New Programme and New Constitution of the Revolutionary Communist Party (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Voices: A Filipino American Oral History (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Little Manila Site Dedication Pamphlet (with inserted note) (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Communist Line (Flat-box 4, Folder 1)
- Kalayaan International (Flat-box 4, Folder 2)
- Come Unity (Flat-box 4, Folder 3)
- Unidad Latina (Flat-box 4, Folder 4)
- The Veteran (Flat-box 4, Folder 5)
- In Struggle (Flat-box 4, Folder 6)
- Bay Area Asian Coalition Against The War (Flat-box 4, Folder 7)
- Rodan (Flat-box 4, Folder 8)
- Why An Asian War? (Flat-box 4, Folder 9)
- Da Zhong Bao (English Section) (Flat-box 4, Folder 10)
- Honolulu Star Bulletin (Pearl Harbor) (Flat-box 4, Folder 11)
- Photographs (from "Bill") of Tule Lake Site (Flat-box 5, Folder 1)
- New Dawn V. 1 (Flat-box 5, Folder 2)
- New Dawn V. 2 (Flat-box 5, Folder 3)
- New Dawn V. 3 (Flat-box 5, Folder 4)
- New Dawn V. 4 (Flat-box 5, Folder 5)
- New Dawn V. 5 (Flat-box 5, Folder 6)
- New Dawn V. 6 (Flat-box 5, Folder 7)
- Gidra 1969 (Flat-box 6, Folder 1)
- Gidra 1970 (Flat-box 6, Folder 2)
- Gidra 1971 (Flat-box 6, Folder 3)
- Gidra 1972 (Flat-box 6, Folder 4)
- Gidra 1973 (Flat-box 6, Folder 5)
- Gidra 1974 (Flat-box 6, Folder 6)
- Gidra 1990 (Flat-box 6, Folder 7)
- Getting Together V. 1-4 (Flat-box 7)
- Getting Together V. 5-9 (Flat-box 8)
- Miscellaneous T-Shirts (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Posters (Map-folder 10)
  Scope and Contents
  Please note: many have evidence of evidence of display and are damaged and or fragile.
  [color photocopies of WWII Allied propaganda]
  Asian/Pacific Students Taking a Stand in '84: California Statewide Asian/Pacific Student Union Conference, March 3, 1984 (Little Tokyo Art Workshop, L.A.)
  Sanrizuka [graphic of plane flying into crosshairs]
  Asian American Music: Joannne & Chris; Hey Bro from L.A. [etc.] Stanford Branner Hall May 29th
  One Struggle - Many Fronts. Defeat U.S. Aggression. Bay Area Asian Coalition - Red Banner Collective (fragile/damaged)
  One Struggle - Many Fronts. Hiroshima - Nagasaki - Indochina. Stop The Genocide of Asian People (water damage)
  [International Hotel] Manilatown Heritage Foundation, 23rd Anniversary Commemoration August 6, 2000
  Save the International Hotel. Low Cost Is A Right of the People (1972 People's Press)
  Long Live the International Hotel! March & Rally - October 9th (International Hotel Tenants Association - International Hotel Support Committee)
  Committee Against Nihonmachi Eviction (Cane) Principles
  Relocation Sites (copy of Western Defense Command & 4th Army - Wartime Civil Control Administration map)
  Join the 1979 Tule Lake Pilgrimage & Plaque Dedication (Tule Lake Committee)
  The Other Side of Infamy [graphic of watchtower at camp]
  Any Day Now - The April 3rd Movement (fragile/damaged)
  If We Worry About What's Going To Happen ... [quote and photograph of Bobby Seale] (Berkeley Graphic Arts)
  May Day, May 1, 1969. Free Huey Day. Mass Rally, Federal Building, San Francisco (fragile/damaged)
  Hasher Power - No Business As Usual [stencil on newsprint]
- Miscellaneous film posters (inscribed to Nagai) (Map-folder 11)
- Asian Americans: A Guide to Library Resources (Stanford) Manuscript (Box 12, Folder 1)
- National Filipino American Youth Association - 7th Annual Conference (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Asian American Jazz Festival (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Reader on History of Pilipinos in America (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Prairie Fire (Weather Underground) (Box 12, Folder 5)
- The Red Papers (Revolutionary Union) (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Puerto Rican Communist Pamphlets (Box 12, Folder 7)
- The 80s (Communist Workers' Party) (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Crime Among Our People (Pacesetters) (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Marxist-Leninist Pamphlets (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Struggle in the RU (Black Workers' Congress) (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Brown Pride (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Misc. Flyers from 11th Annual APAHE Conference (Box 12, Folder 13)